<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Biol Chem</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jbc</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jbc</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JBC</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Journal of Biological Chemistry</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9258</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1083-351X</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>9650 Rockville Pike, Bethesda, MD 20814, U.S.A.</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20028978</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2844151</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">M109.047720</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M109.047720</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Gene Regulation</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title><italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> cAMP Receptor Protein (Rv3676) Differs from the <named-content content-type="genus-species">Escherichia coli</named-content> Paradigm in Its cAMP Binding and DNA Binding Properties and Transcription Activation Properties<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">*</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN2"><sup><inline-graphic xlink:href="sbox.jpg"/></sup></xref></article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Stapleton</surname>
            <given-names>Melanie</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>&#x2021;</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Haq</surname>
            <given-names>Ihtshamul</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>&#xA7;</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hunt</surname>
            <given-names>Debbie M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>&#xB6;</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Arnvig</surname>
            <given-names>Kristine B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>&#xB6;</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Artymiuk</surname>
            <given-names>Peter J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>&#x2021;</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Buxton</surname>
            <given-names>Roger S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>&#xB6;</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Green</surname>
            <given-names>Jeffrey</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>&#x2021;</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1">From the <label>&#x2021;</label>Department of Molecular Biology and Biotechnology, University of Sheffield, Sheffield, S10 2TN, </aff>
        <aff id="aff2">the <label>&#xA7;</label>Department of Chemistry, University of Sheffield, Sheffield S3 7HF, and </aff>
        <aff id="aff3">the <label>&#xB6;</label>Division of Mycobacterial Research, Medical Research Council National Institute for Medical Research, Mill Hill, London NW7 1AA, United Kingdom</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>1</label> To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel.: <phone>44-144-222-4403</phone>; Fax: <fax>44-144-222-2800</fax>; E-mail: <email>jeff.green@sheffield.ac.uk</email>.</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>5</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>22</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>22</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
      <volume>285</volume>
      <issue>10</issue>
      <fpage>7016</fpage>
      <lpage>7027</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2010 by The American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, Inc.</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <license-p><italic>Author's Choice</italic> - Final version full access.</license-p>
          <license-p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License</ext-link> applies to Author Choice Articles</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="zbc01010007016.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <p>The pathogen <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> produces a burst of cAMP upon infection of macrophages. Bacterial cyclic AMP receptor proteins (CRP) are transcription factors that respond to cAMP by binding at target promoters when cAMP concentrations increase. Rv3676 (CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>) is a CRP family protein that regulates expression of genes (<italic>rpfA</italic> and <italic>whiB1</italic>) that are potentially involved in <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> persistence and/or emergence from the dormant state. Here, the CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> homodimer is shown to bind two molecules of cAMP (one per protomer) at noninteracting sites. Furthermore, cAMP binding by CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> was relatively weak, entropy driven, and resulted in a relatively small enhancement in DNA binding. Tandem CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>-binding sites (CRP1 at -58.5 and CRP2 at -37.5) were identified at the <italic>whiB1</italic> promoter (P<italic>whiB1</italic>). <italic>In vitro</italic> transcription reactions showed that CRP1 is an activating site and that CRP2, which was only occupied in the presence of cAMP or at high CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> concentrations in the absence of cAMP, is a repressing site. Binding of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> to CRP1 was not essential for open complex formation but was required for transcription activation. Thus, these data suggest that binding of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> to the P<italic>whiB1</italic> CRP1 site activates transcription at a step after open complex formation. In contrast, high cAMP concentrations allowed occupation of both CRP1 and CRP2 sites, resulting in inhibition of open complex formation. Thus, <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> CRP has evolved several distinct characteristics, compared with the <named-content content-type="genus-species">Escherichia coli</named-content> CRP paradigm, to allow it to regulate gene expression against a background of high concentrations of cAMP.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Gene/Regulation</kwd>
        <kwd>Signal Transduction/Adenylate Cyclase</kwd>
        <kwd>Signal Transduction/Cyclic Nucleotides/Cyclic AMP</kwd>
        <kwd>Transcription/Bacteria</kwd>
        <kwd>Transcription/Promoter</kwd>
        <kwd>Transcription/Regulation</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p><italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> is one of the most successful human pathogens, contributing to the deaths of ~2 million people per annum by causing tuberculosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). It is an adaptable bacterium capable of survival in its preferred environment, the interior of a macrophage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>), and within droplet nuclei in the atmosphere that are produced by infected individuals. The disease is spread by inhalation of such droplets, and following initial infection, <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> can persist in a nonreplicating state from which it may emerge when conditions are more favorable (<italic>e.g.</italic> when the immune system is suppressed), a phenomenon known as reactivation tuberculosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). This strategy has been so successful that the reservoir of infection is thought to be as great as one-third of the world's population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>), and thus the potential for reactivation tuberculosis is very large.</p><p>Appropriate gene regulation is likely to be vital for establishing and emerging from the dormant state. The presence of &gt;100 regulator proteins, 11 two-component systems, 6 serine-threonine protein kinases, and 13 alternative sigma factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>) suggests that transcription regulation is important for <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> pathogenesis. Cyclic AMP is likely to be an important signaling molecule in <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> because it is predicted to possess 17 genes encoding adenylyl cyclases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>), at least one of which, Rv0386, is required for virulence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>). Interestingly, cAMP levels increase upon infection of macrophages by pathogenic mycobacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>), and furthermore, addition of cAMP to cultures of <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> causes changes in gene expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). Recently, Bishai and co-workers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>) showed that upon infection of macrophages, a bacterially derived cAMP burst promotes bacterial survival by interfering with host signaling pathways, but as well as influencing host regulatory networks, cAMP is also important in bacterial gene regulation.</p><p>The best characterized bacterial cAMP-responsive transcriptional regulator is the <named-content content-type="genus-species">Escherichia coli</named-content> cyclic AMP receptor protein (CRP,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN3"><sup>2</sup></xref> sometimes known as catabolite gene activator protein). <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> CRP is activated by binding cAMP and controls aspects of carbon metabolism and virulence gene expression and may act as a more general chromosome organizer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10"> - </xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>). In <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> under conditions of glucose starvation, intracellular cAMP concentrations increase via a mechanism involving interactions between the glucose phosphotransferase system transporter and adenylyl cyclase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>). Cyclic AMP is bound by the <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> CRP dimer resulting in enhanced recognition of a specific DNA sequence (TGTGANNNNNNTCACA) present within the promoter regions of target genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>). At activated promoters, CRP recruits RNA polymerase (RNAP) and promotes transcription by establishing specific protein-protein contacts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>).</p><p>The <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> Rv3676 protein (hereafter CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>) is a member of the CRP family (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16"> - </xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> is 32% identical (53% similar) over 189 amino acids to <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> CRP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>). Like CRP in <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content>, CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> is a global transcriptional regulator because a deletion mutant has altered transcription of a large number of genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>). Moreover, it is implicated in the virulence of <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> because the CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> mutant is attenuated for growth in mice and macrophages as well as <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>). Polymorphisms in CRP that enhance DNA binding have also occurred in the Bacillus Calmette-Guerin vaccine strain of <italic>Mycobacterium bovis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19"> - </xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>) and result in changes in transcription of a number of genes, which, although not contributing to the attenuation of Bacillus Calmette-Guerin, may have been selected by growth <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>).</p><p>In the CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> mutant, the largest decreases in expression were for the <italic>rpfA</italic> and <italic>whiB1</italic> genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>). <italic>In vivo</italic> and <italic>in vitro</italic> analyses indicated that CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> activates expression of <italic>rpfA</italic> and <italic>whiB1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). These are potentially significant observations because <italic>rpfA</italic> encodes a protein that is thought to be involved in reviving dormant bacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>), and <italic>whiB1</italic> encodes a Wbl family protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>). Wbl proteins are found only in actinomycetes and bind redox-sensitive iron-sulfur clusters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>). The mechanism(s) of action of Wbl proteins is still unclear; some have been reported to have protein-disulfide reductase activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>), and at least one (WhiB3) has been shown to bind DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>), consistent with the suggestion that Wbl proteins are transcription factors that might function in the control of developmental processes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>). This latter suggestion raises the possibility that CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> in complex with cAMP regulates genes involved in the developmental switch associated with <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> persistence and/or emergence from the dormant state. However, previous work suggested that although CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> binds cAMP, this interaction induces a relatively small enhancement in specific DNA binding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16"> - </xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). Thus, there are differences between <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> CRP, where the presence of cAMP enhances specific DNA binding by several orders of magnitude (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>), and CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>. Hence, the aim of this work was to investigate the interaction between CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> and cAMP and determine the mechanism of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>-mediated activation of <italic>whiB1</italic> expression. Here, the following points are shown: (i) CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> dimer binds two molecules of cAMP; (ii) unlike <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> CRP, the CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> cAMP-binding sites do not interact; (iii) CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> binds at two immediately adjacent sites in the <italic>whiB1</italic> promoter; and (iv) occupation of the upstream CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>-binding site at low cAMP concentrations activates <italic>whiB1</italic> transcription at a step after open complex formation, whereas occupation of the downstream site at high cAMP concentrations antagonizes activation from the upstream site by preventing open complex formation. In addition, a molecular model based on the <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> CRP structure provides a plausible explanation for the distinctive cAMP binding properties of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES</title><sec><title/><sec><title/><sec><title>Bacterial Strains, Plasmids, and Growth Conditions</title><p>Bacterial strains and plasmids are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>. <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> cultures were grown in Luria-Bertani (LB) medium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>) in a 1:5 volume/flask ratio at 37  degrees C with shaking at 250 rpm, except for <italic>in vivo</italic> transcription experiments where strains were grown in a 1:25 volume/flask ratio. Where required, antibiotics were added to media at the following concentrations: tetracycline 35 mug ml<sup>-1</sup>, kanamycin 50 mug ml<sup>-1</sup>, ampicillin 100 mug ml<sup>-1</sup>. <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> cultures (100 ml) were grown in 1 liter of polycarbonate culture bottles (Techmate) in a Bellco roll-in incubator (2 rpm) at 37  degrees C in Dubos broth containing 0.05% (v/v) Tween 80 supplemented with 0.2% (v/v) glycerol and 4% Dubos medium albumin. Where required, kanamycin was added at a final concentration of 25 mug ml<sup>-1</sup>. <italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic> was grown to log phase (56 h) in LB medium in a 1:5 volume/flask ratio at 37  degrees C with shaking at 250 rpm.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>TABLE 1</label><caption><p><bold>Bacterial strains and plasmids</bold></p><p>IPTG is isopropyl 1-thio-beta -<sc>d</sc>-galactopyranoside.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strain or plasmid</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relevant characteristics</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source or Ref.</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> strains</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;BL21 (lambdaDE3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lysogen of lambdaDE3 carrying a copy of the T7 RNAP under the control of the IPTG-inducible <italic>lacUV5</italic> promoter</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Novagen</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;JRG5876</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BL21 (lambdaDE3) Delta<italic>cyaA</italic>; kan<sup>R</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This work</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;JRG6015</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JRG5876 pGS2132</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This work</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;M182</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> K12 Delta<italic>lac</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;JRG2630</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M182 Delta <italic>crp</italic> derivative</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;JRG5875</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M182 Delta<italic>crp</italic>Delta<italic>cyaA</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This work</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;JRG6016</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JRG2630 p2130 ptac85</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This work</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;JRG6017</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JRG2630 p2130 pGS1645</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This work</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;JRG6018</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JRG5875 p2130 ptac85</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This work</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;JRG6019</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JRG5875 p2130 pGS1645</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This work</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> strains</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;H37Rv</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild-type virulent strain</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;DeltaRv3676</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H37Rv, deletion of <italic>Rv3676</italic> (CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;H37Rv/pRB142</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H37Rv, with <italic>whiB1-lacZ</italic> reporter plasmid pRB142</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This work</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;H37Rv/pRB143</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H37Rv, with <italic>whiB1-lacZ</italic>reporter plasmid pRB143</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This work</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;H37Rv/pRB144</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H37Rv, with <italic>whiB1-lacZ</italic> reporter plasmid pRB144</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This work</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;H37Rv/pRB145</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H37Rv, with <italic>whiB1-lacZ</italic> reporter plasmid pRB145</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This work</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;H37Rv/pRB146</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H37Rv, with <italic>whiB1-lacZ</italic> reporter plasmid pRB146</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This work</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;DeltaRv3676/pRB142</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DeltaRv3676, with <italic>whiB1-lacZ</italic>reporter plasmid pRB142</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This work</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M. smegmatis</italic>strains</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;mc<sup>2</sup> 155</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source of RNAP</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> plasmids</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;pCR4Blunt-TOPO</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General cloning vector for blunt-ended PCR products; Ap<sup>R</sup>, Kan<sup>R</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Invitrogen</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;pET28a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">His<sub>6</sub> tag overexpression vector; Kan<sup>R</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Novagen</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;pRW50</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>lacZ</italic> transcriptional reporter plasmid; Tet<sup>R</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;ptac85</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Expression vector with an IPTG-inducible promoter; Ap<sup>R</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;pGS1645</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ptac85 containing <italic>Rv3676</italic> gene</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This work</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;pGS2060</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pCR4Blunt-TOPO containing the region upstream of <italic>whiB1</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This work</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;p2130</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pRW50 containing <italic>CCgal</italic>Delta<italic>4</italic>, a derivative of <italic>galP1</italic> with a consensus CRP-binding site centered at position -37.5 bp</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;pGS2132</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pET28a derivative encoding His<sub>6</sub>-CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> fusion protein; Ap<sup>R</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This work</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;pGS2060</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pCR4Blunt-TOPO containing the 285-bp region upstream of <italic>whiB1</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This work</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;pGS2061</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">As pGS2060 but with CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> site 1 altered to AGTTAGATAGCCAACG</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This work</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;p2225</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">As pGS2060 but with CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> site 2 altered to CCAAACACTATTGACA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This work</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;p2227</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">As pGS2060 but with CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> site 1 and site 2 altered</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This work</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M. tuberculosis</italic>shuttle plasmids</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;pEJ414</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>lacZ</italic> transcriptional reporter plasmid; Kan<sup>R</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E. O. Davis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;pRB142</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pEJ414 derivative containing transcriptional fusion of <italic>whiB1</italic> upstream region with <italic>lacZ</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This work</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;pRB143</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pRB142 with mutated CRP1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This work</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;pRB144</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pRB142 with mutated CRP2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This work</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;pRB145</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pRB142 with mutated CRP1 and CRP2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This work</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;pRB146</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pRB142 with improved CRP2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This work</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Overproduction and Purification of CRP<sup>Mt</sup></title><p>The CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> (Rv3676) open reading frame was amplified by PCR using primers Myc1746 (5'-CATCATGAATTCGTGGACGAGATCCTGGCC-3') and Myc1747 (5'-CATCATACTCGAGCACTATTACCTCGCTCGGCGGGC-3') containing engineered EcoRI and XhoI sites, respectively. This fragment was ligated into the corresponding sites of a pET28a derivative, in which the kanamycin resistance gene had been disrupted by the insertion of an ampicillin resistance gene (<italic>bla</italic>). The resulting plasmid (pGS2132) encoded a His<sub>6</sub>-CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> fusion protein. The plasmid pGS2132 was moved into <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> strain JRG5876 (BL21 lambdaDE3 Delta<italic>cyaA</italic>), for expression of the recombinant protein by addition of 1 m<sc>m</sc> isopropyl 1-thio-beta-<sc>d</sc>-galactopyranoside, followed by a further 3-h growth at 37  degrees C before collecting the bacteria by centrifugation. The bacteria were lysed by resuspending in 20 m<sc>m</sc> sodium phosphate, pH 7.2, containing 0.5 <sc>m</sc> NaCl, followed by repeated freeze-thawing and sonication. The lysate was cleared by centrifugation, and the resulting cell-free extract was passed through a nickel-charged Hi-Trap chelating column (GE Healthcare). The recombinant His<sub>6</sub>-CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> protein was eluted using an imidazole gradient (0 - 500 m<sc>m</sc> in 20 ml). The pooled fractions containing His<sub>6</sub>-CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> were dialyzed in phosphate-buffered saline (137 m<sc>m</sc> NaCl, 2.7 m<sc>m</sc> KCl, 10 m<sc>m</sc> Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>, 2 m<sc>m</sc> KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>), and 10% (v/v) glycerol was added to the protein before storage at -20  degrees C. Where indicated the His<sub>6</sub> tag was removed by treatment with the protease thrombin (10 units for 16 h at 4  degrees C).</p></sec><sec><title>Trypsin Digestion of His<sub>6</sub>-CRP<sup>Mt</sup></title><p>Recombinant His<sub>6</sub>-CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> (15 mug) was incubated with 2 m<sc>m</sc> cAMP or cGMP for 10 min at 37  degrees C, followed by the addition of a second cyclic nucleotide (2 m<sc>m</sc>) for 10 min where indicated. The protein was then cleaved with 1 mug of trypsin (Sigma) for up to 10 min at 20  degrees C, and the reaction was stopped by the addition of 1.3% SDS and heating to 100  degrees C for 10 min. The resulting fragments were analyzed on a 15% SDS-polyacrylamide gel.</p></sec><sec><title>Isothermal Calorimetry</title><p>Recombinant His<sub>6</sub>-CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> was extensively dialyzed against phosphate-buffered saline, and the concentration of protein was determined by SDS-PAGE and amino acid analysis (ion exchange chromatography and ninhydrin detection). The sodium salt of cAMP was dissolved in the dialysate phosphate-buffered saline, and the concentration was determined by UV absorption spectroscopy using the extinction coefficient of &#x3F5;<sub>260</sub> of 1.23 x 10<sup>4</sup> <sc>m</sc><sup>-1</sup> cm<sup>-1</sup>. All samples were centrifuged prior to the titrations. The titration calorimetry measurements were performed using a MicroCal VP-ITC (MicroCal LLC, Northampton, MA). The isothermal calorimetry sample cell (cell volume 1.4 ml) was loaded with 84 mu<sc>m</sc> His<sub>6</sub>-CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>. After a suitable period of thermal equilibration (25  degrees C), 18 injections of 15 mul of 0.87 m<sc>m</sc> cAMP were introduced into the protein solution every 6 min with continual stirring and an initial delay of 2 min. A small preinjection of 3 mul was also made to expel any air bubbles that may have accumulated during equilibration. In a separate control experiment, aliquots of the cAMP solution were titrated into the dialysis buffer to determine whether the ligand exhibited heat of dilution. Data analysis and fitting were done using Origin 7.0 (MicroCal LLC), and corrected binding isotherms were best fit using a single set of identical binding sites model as described by Wiseman <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Transfer of Plasmids, Preparation of Cell-free Extracts, and Assay for beta-Galactosidase in M. tuberculosis</title><p>These were carried out as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>). beta-Galactosidase assays on log phase cultures (<italic>A</italic><sub>600 nm</sub> ~ 0.5) were done according to Miller (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>). Three independent cultures were analyzed for each strain.</p></sec><sec><title>5'-Rapid Amplification of cDNA Ends</title><p>5'-Rapid amplification of cDNA ends was performed using the 5'-rapid amplification of cDNA ends system from Invitrogen according to the manufacturer's instructions. DNA-free RNA (5 mug) from <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> H37Rv was reverse-transcribed with GSP1 (5'-TACGGGCTTTCGTGCG-3') using Superscript II reverse transcriptase. The cDNA was purified on a SNAP column and tailed with dCTP using terminal deoxynucleotidyltransferase. The tailed cDNA was amplified using Platinum (R)  Taq with primers GSP2 (5'-CGCCGCTCGTCTTCGCTCAT-3') and AAP (5'-GGCCACGCGTCGACTAGTACGGGIIGGGIIGGGIIG-3'). The product was visualized on a 1.5% agarose gel, and a band of ~300 bp was excised and sequenced.</p></sec><sec><title>Construction of Reporter Gene Plasmids Using the Upstream Region of whiB1</title><p>The region of the DNA sequence upstream of <italic>whiB1</italic> was generated by PCR from <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> genomic DNA using the primer pairs Myc896 (5'-GCTCTAGAGCAAGAAAGCGGATCTG-3') and Myc487 (5'-GCAAGCTTGCCTTGTGGCGCCAATC-3') (bp 3,595,415 - 3,595,731). This fragment was ligated into the XbaI and HindIII sites of the polylinker in the <italic>lacZ</italic> transcriptional reporter plasmid pEJ414 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>) to make pRB142 (P<italic>whiB1</italic>). This construct was verified by DNA sequencing.</p></sec><sec><title>Mutagenesis of CRP-binding Site in Plasmid pRB142</title><p>This was performed using the Stratagene QuikChange mutagenesis kit. To mutagenize CRP1 (AGTGAGATAGCCCACG to AGTtAGATAGCCaACG), the primers used were Myc898 (5'-AACGAGATCGCCAGAGTTAGATAGCCAACGCGCTTACGTAACAC-3') and Myc899 (5'-GTGTTACGTAAGCGCGTTGGCTATCTAACTCTGGCGATCTCGTT-3') to generate pRB143. To mutagenize CRP2 (CGTAACACTATTGACA to CcaAACACTATTGACA), the primers used were Myc900 (5'-TAGCCCACGCGCTTACCAAACACTATTGACATCTGTTGAGCCTG-3') and Myc901 (5'-CAGGCTCAACAGATGTCAATAGTGTTTGGTAAGCGCGTGGGCTA-3') to generate pRB144. To mutagenize both CRP1 and CRP2, the primers used were Myc963 (5'-CGCCAGAGTTAGATAGCCAACGCGCTTACCAAACACTATTGACATCTGTTG-3') and Myc964 (5'-CAACAGATGTCAATAGTGTTTGGTAAGCGCGTTGGCTATCTAACTCTGGCG-3') to generate pRB145. To improve CRP2 (CGTAACACTATTGACA to CGTgACACTATTGACA), the primers used were 5'-TAGCCCACGCGCTTACGTGACACTATTGACATCTGTTGAGCCTG-3' and 5'-CAGGCTCAACAGATGCACATAGTGTTTGGTAAGCGCGTGGGCTA-3'. Mutagenized constructs were verified by DNA sequencing.</p></sec><sec><title>beta-Galactosidase Assays in E. coli</title><p>Assays were carried out on log phase cultures (<italic>A</italic><sub>600 nm</sub> ~ 0.5) according to Miller (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>). Five independent cultures were analyzed for each strain.</p></sec><sec><title>Electrophoretic Mobility Shift Assays</title><p>The region upstream of the <italic>whiB1</italic> gene was excised from plasmid pGS2060 using restriction enzymes XbaI and HindIII. The resulting fragment was end-labeled using 0.37 MBq of [alpha-<sup>32</sup>P]dGTP, dATP, and Klenow enzyme, and unincorporated radionucleotides were removed using a QIAquick PCR clean-up kit (Qiagen). Radiolabeled DNA (~5 ng) was incubated with 0 - 21 mu<sc>m</sc> His<sub>6</sub>-CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> (or CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> where indicated) and 0 - 2 m<sc>m</sc> cAMP, in the presence of 20 m<sc>m</sc> HEPES, pH 7.5, 0.2 m<sc>m</sc> EDTA, 10 m<sc>m</sc> (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>, 1 m<sc>m</sc> dithiothreitol, 15 m<sc>m</sc> MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 15 m<sc>m</sc> KCl, 0.05 mg ml<sup>-1</sup> bovine serum albumin, and 0.01 unit of poly(dI-dC), for 30 min at 25  degrees C. The resulting complexes were then separated on 6% polyacrylamide gels buffered with 0.5x TBE (45 m<sc>m</sc> Tris borate, 1 m<sc>m</sc> EDTA).</p></sec><sec><title>DNase I Footprinting</title><p>Radiolabeled <italic>whiB1</italic> promoter DNA, or <italic>whiB1</italic> promoters with mutated CRP sites (~100 ng), was incubated with 2.5 - 50 mu<sc>m</sc> His<sub>6</sub>-CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> in the presence of 50 m<sc>m</sc> Tris, pH 7.5, 100 m<sc>m</sc> NaCl, 10 m<sc>m</sc> MgCl<sub>2</sub>, and 2 m<sc>m</sc> cAMP for 30 min at 25  degrees C. Footprinting reactions containing RNAP were done in the presence of 40 m<sc>m</sc> Tris, pH 8.0, 75 m<sc>m</sc> KCl, 10 m<sc>m</sc> MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.1 m<sc>m</sc> EDTA, 1 m<sc>m</sc> dithiothreitol, and 250 mug ml<sup>-1</sup> bovine serum albumin. The complexes were then digested with 1 unit of DNase I for 15 - 60 s at 25  degrees C. Reactions were stopped by the addition of 200 mul of 0.3 <sc>m</sc> sodium acetate, pH 5.2, containing 20 m<sc>m</sc> EDTA, followed by phenol/chloroform extraction. The DNA was ethanol-precipitated and resuspended in loading buffer (80% v/v formamide, 0.1% w/v SDS, 10% v/v glycerol, 8 m<sc>m</sc> EDTA, 0.1% w/v bromphenol blue, 0.1% w/v xylene cyanol) for electrophoretic fractionation on 6% polyacrylamide-urea gels and autoradiographic analysis. Maxam and Gilbert G tracks of the DNA fragments were used to provide a calibration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>In Vitro Transcription Reactions and Permanganate Footprinting</title><p><italic>M. smegmatis</italic> RNAP was isolated by a method adapted from Beaucher <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>). A 6-g wet cell pellet of <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> mc<sup>2</sup> 155 was disrupted by passage through a French pressure cell. The lysate was then centrifuged and subjected to ammonium sulfate precipitation. The resulting cytoplasmic extract was dialyzed against RNAP buffer (50 m<sc>m</sc> Tris-Cl, pH 8.0, 10 mu<sc>m</sc> ZnSO<sub>4</sub>, 1 m<sc>m</sc> EDTA, 10 m<sc>m</sc> MgCl<sub>2</sub>, and 20% glycerol) containing 10 m<sc>m</sc> KCl, before loading onto a 5-ml HiTrap heparin column (GE Healthcare). Elution was achieved by applying a linear gradient of 0.01 - 1 <sc>m</sc> KCl in RNAP buffer, and the fractions containing RNAP, as determined by SDS-PAGE, were pooled. Dialysis and purification were repeated twice, using a 1-ml HiTrap SP HP cation exchange column followed by a 1-ml HiTrap Q HP anion exchange column (GE Healthcare). Fractions containing enriched holo-RNAP, as determined by SDS-PAGE, were desalted into RNAP buffer containing 10 m<sc>m</sc> KCl and concentrated 10-fold using a Vivaspin concentrator (molecular mass cutoff of 5 kDa; Sartorius). The resulting RNAP was then tested in <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription assays (not shown) and stored in 25% glycerol at -80  degrees C.</p><p>For <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription reactions, 0.1 - 1-kb markers were prepared using Perfect RNA Marker template mix (Novagen). A 20-mul reaction containing 0.75 mug of RNA template mix, 80 m<sc>m</sc> HEPES, pH 7.5, 12 m<sc>m</sc> MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 m<sc>m</sc> NaCl, 10 m<sc>m</sc> dithiothreitol, 2 m<sc>m</sc> ATP, 2 m<sc>m</sc> GTP, 2 m<sc>m</sc> CTP, 0.1 m<sc>m</sc> UTP, 5 muCi of [alpha-<sup>32</sup>P]UTP (800 Ci mmol<sup>-1</sup>, PerkinElmer Life Sciences), 20 units of RiboLock RNase inhibitor (Fermentas), and 50 units of T7 RNAP (Novagen), was incubated for 1 h at 37  degrees C, before storing at -20  degrees C. Markers from ~2 ng of template were used for gel calibration.</p><p>The 285-bp region upstream of the <italic>whiB1</italic> gene and the corresponding regions with the altered CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>-binding sites were excised from plasmids pGS2060, pGS2061, p2225, and p2227 using restriction enzymes XbaI and HindIII. These DNA fragments (0.2 pmol) were incubated for 15 min at 37  degrees C in a 21-mul reaction volume containing 40 m<sc>m</sc> Tris-Cl, pH 8.0, 10 m<sc>m</sc> MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 m<sc>m</sc> dithiothreitol, 75 m<sc>m</sc> KCl, 0.1 m<sc>m</sc> EDTA, 5% glycerol, 250 mug ml<sup>-1</sup> bovine serum albumin, 0 - 2 m<sc>m</sc> cAMP, 2 pmol of <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> RNAP, and 0 - 20 mu<sc>m</sc> CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>. Transcription was initiated by the addition of 4 mul of a solution containing UTP at 50 mu<sc>m</sc>; ATP, CTP and GTP at 1 m<sc>m</sc>; and 2.5 muCi of [alpha-<sup>32</sup>P]UTP (800 Ci mmol<sup>-1</sup>, PerkinElmer Life Sciences), followed by incubation for 15 min at 37  degrees C. Reactions were terminated by the addition of 25 mul of Stop/Loading dye solution (95% formamide, 20 m<sc>m</sc> EDTA, pH 8, 0.05% bromphenol blue, 0.05% xylene cyanol) containing 0.1 - 1-kb markers from ~9.5 ng of template as a loading control. Samples (10 mul) of each reaction were loaded onto a 6% acrylamide, 1x TBE, 8 <sc>m</sc> urea gel and analyzed by autoradiography. Autoradiographs were quantified by ImageMaster software (GE Healthcare).</p><p>For permanganate footprinting, the <italic>whiB1</italic> promoter fragment was prepared as for electrophoretic mobility shift assay, except that the opposite strand was end-labeled with [alpha-<sup>32</sup>P]dCTP. The resulting radiolabeled DNA (~20 ng) was incubated at 20  degrees C for 5 min in a reaction containing 40 m<sc>m</sc> Tris-Cl, pH 8.0, 10 m<sc>m</sc> MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 75 m<sc>m</sc> KCl, 0.1 m<sc>m</sc> EDTA, 5% glycerol, 250 mug ml<sup>-1</sup> bovine serum albumin, 0.1 m<sc>m</sc> GTP, 0.1 m<sc>m</sc> UTP, 0 - 2 m<sc>m</sc> cAMP, and 0 - 20 mu<sc>m</sc> His-tagged CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup>. M. smegmatis</italic> RNAP (2 pmol) was added and incubation continued at 37  degrees C for 15 min. KMnO<sub>4</sub> (1 m<sc>m</sc>) was added for 10 min at 37  degrees C, and the reactions were stopped by the addition of 200 mul of 0.3 <sc>m</sc> sodium acetate, pH 5.2, containing 20 m<sc>m</sc> EDTA, followed by phenol/chloroform extraction and ethanol precipitation. The DNA was then incubated with 10% piperidine at 90  degrees C for 10 min before being vacuum-dried and resuspended in loading buffer (80% formamide, 0.1% SDS, 10% glycerol, 8 m<sc>m</sc> EDTA, 0.1% bromphenol blue, 0.1% xylene cyanol) for electrophoretic fractionation on 6% polyacrylamide-urea gels and autoradiographic analysis. A Maxam and Gilbert G track of the DNA fragment was used to provide a calibration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>).</p></sec></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title/><sec><title/><sec><title>Cyclic AMP Binding at Two Independent Sites Enhances CRP<sup>Mt</sup>-DNA Interactions</title><p>Whereas <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> CRP is very responsive to cAMP, exhibiting nonspecific low affinity DNA binding in the absence of cAMP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>), previous reports of the effects of cAMP on the properties of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> have been equivocal. Rickman <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>) and Bai <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>) found significant binding of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> to target DNA in the absence of cAMP and only marginal enhancement upon addition of up to 0.1 m<sc>m</sc> cAMP. In contrast, Agarwal <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>) failed to detect DNA binding in the absence of cAMP, but binding was observed in the presence of 1 m<sc>m</sc> cAMP. Others have shown that incubation with cAMP alters intrinsic tryptophan fluorescence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>) and the polypeptide profiles obtained when CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> is digested with trypsin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>), implying that cAMP causes conformational changes in CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>. To investigate further, we have isolated recombinant His<sub>6</sub>-tagged CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> by overproduction in a <italic>cyaA</italic> mutant of <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content>, which is unable to synthesize cAMP. This cAMP-free CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> protein was then used to determine the polypeptide profiles obtained after digestion of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> with trypsin in the absence and presence of cAMP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref><italic>A</italic>, <italic>lanes 2 - 7</italic>). In contrast to <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> CRP, which is relatively resistant to trypsin cleavage in the absence of cAMP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>), CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> was readily digested by trypsin, yielding a major polypeptide of molecular mass ~16 kDa, as estimated by SDS-PAGE (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref><italic>A</italic>). In the presence of cAMP, the protein was more resistant to proteolysis, and a major polypeptide of molecular mass ~15 kDa was obtained. In the presence of cGMP, the sensitivity of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> to trypsin was similar to that observed in the absence of cAMP, although a different digestion pattern, which included both major polypeptides (~16 and ~15 kDa) observed in the absence and presence of cAMP, was obtained suggesting that cGMP is bound by CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> with concomitant changes in conformation that are different from those invoked by cAMP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref><italic>A</italic>, <italic>lanes 10 - 15</italic>). Significantly, addition of cAMP after preincubation with cGMP for 10 min, or vice versa, resulted in a limited proteolysis pattern identical to that obtained with cAMP alone indicating that cAMP is the preferred ligand (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref><italic>A</italic>, <italic>lanes 20 - 24</italic>). To ensure that the presence of the His<sub>6</sub> tag was not influencing the interaction of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> with cAMP, the His<sub>6</sub> tag was removed by thrombin cleavage, and the partial proteolysis experiments were repeated. This showed that untagged CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> exhibited the same behavior as the tagged protein in the absence (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jbc.org/cgi/content/full/M109.047720/DC1">supplemental Fig. S1, <italic>lanes 3</italic> and <italic>6</italic></ext-link>) and presence (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jbc.org/cgi/content/full/M109.047720/DC1">supplemental Fig. S1, <italic>lanes 4</italic> and <italic>7</italic></ext-link>) of cAMP suggesting that the His<sub>6</sub> tag was not affecting the gross conformational changes induced by cAMP binding. Therefore, the His<sub>6</sub>-tagged form of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> was considered suitable for further ligand binding studies.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>FIGURE 1.</label><caption><p><bold>Characterization of cAMP binding by CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>.</bold> <italic>A</italic>, digestion of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> (15 mug) by trypsin (1 mug) in the presence and absence of cAMP or cGMP (2 m<sc>m</sc>). The composition of the reaction mixtures is indicated <italic>above</italic> each lane of typical Coomassie Blue-stained SDS-polyacrylamide gels. For <italic>lanes 2, 3, 12</italic>, and <italic>13</italic>, the reactions were incubated at 37  degrees C for 1 min. For all other lanes, the reactions were incubated at 37  degrees C for 10 min. <italic>Lanes 1, 8, 9</italic>, and <italic>16</italic> are molecular mass markers; the sizes (kDa) of the relevant markers are shown on the <italic>left</italic> (the full set is 250, 150, 100, 75, 50, 37, 25, 20, 15, and 10 kDa, from <italic>top</italic> to <italic>bottom)</italic>. CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> migrates just above the 25-kDa marker. <italic>Lane 23</italic> shows a reaction in which CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> was preincubated for 10 min with cGMP before adding cAMP and trypsin, indicated by <italic>cGMP then cAMP. Lane 24</italic> shows a reaction in which CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> was preincubated for 10 min with cAMP before adding cGMP and trypsin, indicated by <italic>cAMP then cGMP. B</italic>, analysis of cAMP binding by isothermal calorimetry. The <italic>upper panel</italic> shows the raw binding heats. Integrations of these peaks with respect to time and correction to a per mol basis yield the binding isotherm shown in the <italic>lower panel</italic> (<italic>squares</italic>). Also shown in the lower panel (<italic>triangles</italic>) are the heats of ligand dilution.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0111006990001"/></fig><p>Isothermal calorimetry was used to determine the stoichiometry and affinity of cAMP binding to His<sub>6</sub>-CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>. A typical titration is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref><italic>B</italic>. The data yield good nonlinear least squares fitting to a single set of identical binding sites model and are consistent with each protomer of the CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> dimer binding one cAMP molecule with relatively weak (<italic>K<sub>b</sub></italic> of ~1.7 x 10<sup>4</sup> <sc>m</sc><sup>-1</sup>) affinity. Furthermore, the binding of cAMP is an endothermic reaction (Delta<italic>G<sub>b</sub></italic> -23.7 kJ mol<sup>-1</sup>) with a positive binding enthalpy (Delta<italic>H<sub>b</sub></italic> ~ 30.7 kJ mol<sup>-1</sup>). Therefore, the entropy change <italic>T</italic>Delta<italic>S<sub>b</sub></italic> is ~54.4 kJ mol<sup>-1</sup> K<sup>-1</sup>, and hence cAMP binding is entropically driven. Chemical cross-linking showed that CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> is a dimer (not shown), and thus the data indicate that unlike the <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> CRP dimer, the two cAMP-binding sites in the CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> dimer are independent.</p><p>The effect of cAMP binding on the ability of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> to bind DNA <italic>in vivo</italic> was tested in the heterologous host <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> because <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> has 17 predicted adenylyl cyclase proteins, and <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> has only one, CyaA; and thus it is possible to simply create a cAMP-free background for these experiments. The parent <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> strain was a <italic>crp lac</italic> double mutant into which a <italic>cyaA</italic> mutation was introduced. The readout (beta-galactosidase activity) from the simple CRP-repressed promoter CCgalDelta4, which contains a consensus CRP site that is recognized by CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> located such that occupation of this site occludes the promoter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>), was used as a measure of the DNA binding activity of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> as shown previously by Spreadbury <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). In the CyaA<sup>+</sup> and CyaA<sup>-</sup> strains containing the vector (ptac85), transcription from the reporter was similar (761  +-  24 and 722  +-  25 Miller units, respectively, <italic>n</italic> = 5). However, in the presence of the CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> expression plasmid (pGS1645), reporter transcription was ~60% lower (323  +-  86 Miller units, <italic>n</italic> = 5) in the Cya<sup>+</sup> strain compared with that observed in the absence of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>, consistent with the observations of Spreadbury <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). However, in the <italic>cyaA</italic> mutant, which is unable to synthesize cAMP, the readout from the reporter in the presence of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> increased by ~2-fold (613  +-  20 Miller units, <italic>n</italic> = 5) compared with the Cya<sup>+</sup> strain to reach ~80% of the activity observed in the absence of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>. These data are consistent with cAMP enhancing DNA binding of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup> in vivo</italic>.</p><p>To investigate the effect of cAMP on CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> DNA binding <italic>in vitro</italic>, preliminary electrophoretic mobility shift assays were used to show that CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> formed at least two complexes at the <italic>whiB1</italic> promoter in the absence and presence of cAMP but that DNA binding was enhanced in the presence of cAMP (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jbc.org/cgi/content/full/M109.047720/DC1">supplemental Fig. S2<italic>A</italic></ext-link>). Furthermore, in cAMP titration experiments, CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> binding to the <italic>whiB1</italic> promoter was enhanced when the cAMP concentration exceeded 0.05 m<sc>m</sc> (not shown), consistent with the isothermal calorimetry experiments. Moreover, the presence of the His<sub>6</sub> tag did not significantly affect DNA binding by CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> in the absence (not shown) and presence of cAMP (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jbc.org/cgi/content/full/M109.047720/DC1">supplemental Fig. S2<italic>B</italic></ext-link>). Thus, the His<sub>6</sub>-tagged form was used in further DNA binding studies.</p><p>In summary, the work described above shows the following: (i) that CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> binds two cAMP molecules per dimer (one per subunit); (ii) that the cAMP-binding sites act independently; and (iii) that cAMP binding induces conformational changes in the CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> dimer that enhance specific DNA binding <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>whiB1 Promoter Contains Two CRP<sup>Mt</sup>-binding Sites</title><p>The <italic>whiB1</italic> gene encodes a Wbl (WhiB-like) protein. These proteins have iron-sulfur clusters and are found only in actinomycetes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>) where they are thought to function as transcription factors and/or as protein-disulfide reductases. The <italic>whiB1</italic> transcript was less abundant in a CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>), implying that CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> activates <italic>whiB1</italic> expression, which was confirmed using a <italic>whiB1-lacZ</italic> fusion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). 5'-Rapid amplification of cDNA ends was used to confirm that the <italic>whiB1</italic> transcript start was located at 109 or 110 bp upstream of the translational start as reported by Agarwal <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>) (data not shown). The electrophoretic mobility shift assays (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jbc.org/cgi/content/full/M109.047720/DC1">supplemental Fig. S2<italic>A</italic></ext-link>) suggested the presence of more than one CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>-binding site in the <italic>whiB1</italic> promoter. Inspection of the <italic>whiB1</italic> promoter region indicated the presence of two potential CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>-binding sites upstream of the transcript start (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). The first site (CRP1) located at -58.5 relative to the transcript start matches the proposed CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> consensus (NGTGNNANNNNNCACA) of Rickman <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>) in seven of the eight defined bases (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). The second potential site (CRP2) is a poorer match to the consensus (six of the eight defined bases are matched) and is located at -37.5 relative to the transcript start. The CRP1 site has previously been implicated in CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>-dependent activation of <italic>whiB1</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>).</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>FIGURE 2.</label><caption><p><bold>Nucleotide sequence of the <italic>whiB1</italic> promoter region (P<italic>whiB1</italic>).</bold> Diagram of the nucleotide sequence of P<italic>whiB1</italic> showing the transcript start (<italic>tsp</italic>) and its associated extended -10 region and -35 region (<italic>underlined</italic>), two CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>-binding sites (<italic>boxed</italic>), and the ribosome-binding site (<italic>RBS</italic>). The locations of the nucleotides within the CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>-binding sites that were replaced to impair the sites as indicated in the text are <italic>overlined</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0111006990002"/></fig><p>DNase I footprinting showed that both CRP1 and CRP2 sites in the <italic>whiB1</italic> promoter were recognized by CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> and that binding to both sites was enhanced in the presence of cAMP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref><italic>A</italic>). Titration of the <italic>whiB1</italic> promoter with increasing concentrations of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> showed that the CRP1 site (-70 to -51) was occupied before the CRP2 site (-50 to -29) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref><italic>A</italic>). Furthermore, mutation of CRP1 (indicated by lowercase letters, AGTGAGATAGCCCACG to AGTtAGATAGCCaACG) or CRP2 (CGTAACACTATTGACA to CcaAACACTATTGACA) inhibited binding of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> to these sites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref><italic>B</italic>). Inactivation of CRP1 also impaired, but did not abolish, binding to CRP2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref><italic>B</italic>, compare <italic>lane 5</italic> with <italic>6</italic>). Thus, it was concluded: (i) the <italic>whiB1</italic> promoter possesses tandem CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> sites, (ii) binding to these sites is enhanced in the presence of cAMP; and (iii) occupation of CRP2 is improved by occupation of CRP1.</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>FIGURE 3.</label><caption><p><bold>Identification of two CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>-binding sites within P<italic>whiB1</italic>.</bold> <italic>A</italic>, <italic>whiB1</italic> promoter (P<italic>whiB1</italic>) has two CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>-binding sites. <italic>Lanes 2 - 6</italic> show reactions in the presence of 2 m<sc>m</sc> cAMP; <italic>lanes 7 - 11</italic> show reactions in the absence of cAMP. <italic>Lane 1</italic> shows no CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>; <italic>lanes 2</italic> and <italic>7</italic> show 2.5 mu<sc>m</sc> CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>; <italic>lanes 3</italic> and <italic>8</italic> show 5 mu<sc>m</sc> CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>; <italic>lanes 4</italic> and <italic>9</italic> show 10 mu<sc>m</sc> CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>; <italic>lanes 5</italic> and <italic>10</italic> show 25 mu<sc>m</sc> CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>; <italic>lanes 6</italic> and <italic>11</italic> show 50 mu<sc>m</sc> CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>; <italic>lane 12</italic> shows Maxam and Gilbert G track. <italic>WT</italic>, wild type. <italic>B</italic>, mutation of P<italic>whiB1</italic> CRP1 impairs binding of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> to CRP2. All reactions contained cAMP (2 m<sc>m</sc>). <italic>Lanes 1 - 4</italic> show reactions of the indicated promoter variants in the absence of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> as follows: -<italic>1</italic>, CRP1 site impaired (AGTGAGATAGCCCACG to AGTtAGATAGCCaACG); -<italic>2</italic>, CRP2 site impaired (CGTAACACTATTGACA to CcaAACACTATTGACA), and -<italic>12</italic>, both sites impaired. <italic>Lanes 5 - 8</italic>, DNase I footprints in the presence of 50 mu<sc>m</sc> CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup>. Lanes 9 - 12</italic>, Maxam and Gilbert G tracks. The locations of the CRP1 and CRP2 sites (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>) are indicated by <italic>boxes</italic>. The footprints shown are typical of at least three experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0111006990003"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Both CRP<sup>Mt</sup>-binding Sites in the whiB1 Promoter Are Functional</title><p>The DNase I footprinting studies indicated that there are two <italic>CRP<sup>Mt</sup></italic> sites in the <italic>whiB1</italic> promoter. The functionality of the sites was tested by <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription experiments. Transcription from the <italic>whiB1</italic> promoter in the presence of <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> RNAP was low (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref><italic>A</italic>, <italic>lane 3</italic>). At low concentrations of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>, <italic>whiB1</italic> transcription was enhanced, but at higher concentrations CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> inhibited transcription (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref><italic>A</italic>, <italic>lanes 4 - 8</italic>). This same pattern of regulation was observed with the untagged form of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jbc.org/cgi/content/full/M109.047720/DC1">supplemental Fig. S3, compare <italic>lanes 3 - 6</italic> and <italic>lanes 7 - 10</italic></ext-link>), indicating that the presence of the His<sub>6</sub> tag does not alter the transcriptional behavior of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>. A similar transcription profile was observed in the presence of cAMP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref><italic>A</italic>, <italic>lanes 9 - 16</italic>) except for the following: (i) there was a reproducible decrease in basal transcription (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref><italic>A</italic>, compare <italic>lanes 3</italic> and <italic>11</italic>), and (ii) the response curve was shifted to the left, with maximum <italic>whiB1</italic> expression occurring in the presence of 1.3 mu<sc>m</sc> CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> in the presence of cAMP compared with 2.5 mu<sc>m</sc> CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> in the absence of cAMP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref><italic>B</italic>). This result is consistent with cAMP enhancing CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> binding to both CRP1 and CRP2 sites in the <italic>whiB1</italic> promoter. In conjunction with the footprinting experiments described above, these data were interpreted to mean that binding to the high affinity CRP1 site activates <italic>whiB1</italic> transcription, whereas occupation of both CRP1 and CRP2 sites inhibits <italic>whiB1</italic> transcription. This conclusion was supported by <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription reactions with <italic>whiB1</italic> promoters carrying mutations in CRP1 and/or CRP2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref><italic>C</italic>). At a low CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> concentration (2.5 mu<sc>m</sc>) in the absence of cAMP, the footprinting evidence indicates that CRP1 will be occupied at the wild-type promoter. Under these conditions, mutation of the CRP1 site decreased transcription of <italic>whiB1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>, <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic>, <italic>lanes 1</italic> and <italic>2</italic>). Under the same conditions, mutation of CRP2 slightly enhanced <italic>whiB1</italic> transcription (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>, <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic>, <italic>lanes 1</italic> and <italic>3</italic>). A similar pattern was observed in the presence of cAMP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>, <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic>, <italic>lanes 5 - 7</italic>). At a higher CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> concentration (20 mu<sc>m</sc>), the footprints indicate that both CRP1 and CRP2 will be occupied. Under these conditions, impairment of CRP1 had little effect on transcription compared with the wild-type promoter, <italic>i.e.</italic> transcription remained low (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>, <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic>, <italic>lanes 9</italic> and <italic>10</italic> and <italic>lanes 13</italic> and <italic>14</italic>). However, impairment of CRP2 enhanced transcription of <italic>whiB1</italic> compared with the wild-type promoter under these conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>, <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic>, <italic>lanes 9</italic> and <italic>11</italic>, and <italic>lanes 13</italic> and <italic>15</italic>). Hence, these observations suggest that occupation of CRP2 is sufficient to repress basal transcription from P<italic>whiB1</italic>. In the presence of cAMP, mutation of both CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> sites resulted in transcription similar to that of the unaltered promoter in the absence of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>, <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic>, <italic>lanes 8</italic> and <italic>16</italic>). In the absence of cAMP, transcription from the <italic>whiB1</italic> promoter with both CRP1 and CRP2 impaired was lower than from the unaltered promoter in the absence of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>, suggesting that in the absence of cAMP there is still some unproductive interaction between CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> and the altered <italic>whiB1</italic> promoter despite the impairment of both CRP-binding sites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>, <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic>, <italic>lanes 4</italic> and <italic>12</italic>). Note that transcription in the absence of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> for all the altered promoters was the same as that for the unaltered <italic>whiB1</italic> promoter, indicating that the changes to the sequences of the CRP sites had not affected the basal level of transcription (data not shown).</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>FIGURE 4.</label><caption><p><bold><italic>In vitro</italic></bold> <bold>transcription from P<italic>whiB1</italic> is activated by CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> occupation of CRP1 and inhibited by CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> occupation of CRP2.</bold> Reactions were carried out as described under "Experimental Procedures" with the amounts of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> used shown <italic>below</italic> each lane. <italic>A</italic>, typical autoradiograph showing the effects of increasing concentrations of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> on <italic>whiB1</italic> transcription <italic>in vitro. B</italic>, using the control as the standard, the relative amount of <italic>whiB1</italic> transcript in each of the reactions shown in <italic>A</italic> was quantified and plotted as a <italic>histogram. Open bars</italic>, no cAMP; <italic>filled bars</italic>, 2 m<sc>m</sc> cAMP. <italic>C</italic>, <italic>autoradiograph</italic> showing the effects of mutation of the <italic>whiB1</italic> CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>-binding sites on transcription. The <italic>whiB1</italic> promoter variants are as described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref><italic>B</italic>. The control and the <italic>whiB1</italic> transcript are indicated. WT, wild type. <italic>D</italic>, using the amount of transcript formed in the absence of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> as the base line, the amount of transcript formed under the indicated conditions was quantified and plotted as a <italic>histogram</italic> (<italic>black bars</italic>, wild-type promoter; <italic>gray bars</italic>, CRP1 impaired; <italic>stippled bars</italic>, CRP2 impaired; <italic>open bars</italic>, CRP1 and CRP2 impaired). The <italic>in vitro</italic> transcriptions shown are typical of at least three experiments. The amount of transcription relative to that observed in the absence of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> was calculated by dividing the mean of the test condition by that measured in the absence of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> and expressing this value as a fold difference.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0111006990004"/></fig><p>The <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription experiments showed that CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> acts as both an activator (at low concentrations) and repressor (at high concentrations) of <italic>whiB1</italic> expression. Permanganate footprinting to detect open complex formation showed the presence of quantitatively similar distortions of DNA at nucleotide T -8 in the <italic>whiB1</italic> promoter mediated by RNAP in the presence or absence of 2.5 mu<sc>m</sc> CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref><italic>A</italic>, <italic>lanes 3, 4, 8</italic>, and <italic>9</italic>). This evidence suggests that CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>-mediated activation of <italic>whiB1</italic> expression probably occurs after open complex formation, because in the absence of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> transcription from the <italic>whiB1</italic> promoter is low (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref><italic>A</italic>, compare <italic>lanes 3</italic> and <italic>4</italic>). In the presence of 20 mu<sc>m</sc> CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>, the open complex was not detected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref><italic>A</italic>, <italic>lanes 5</italic> and <italic>10</italic>) indicating that higher concentrations of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> inhibit <italic>whiB1</italic> expression at a point before open complex formation, probably by inhibiting RNAP binding.</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>FIGURE 5.</label><caption><p><bold><italic>M. tuberculosis</italic></bold> <bold>CRP activates <italic>whiB1</italic> transcription after open complex formation.</bold> <italic>A</italic>, permanganate footprints were obtained with P<italic>whiB1</italic> in the presence and absence of <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> RNAP and CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup>. Lanes 1</italic> and <italic>6</italic> show CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> 2.5 mu<sc>m</sc> only; <italic>lanes 2</italic> and <italic>7</italic> show CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> 20 mu<sc>m</sc> only; <italic>lanes 3</italic> and <italic>8</italic> show RNAP only; <italic>lanes 4</italic> and <italic>9</italic> show RNAP plus CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> 2.5 mu<sc>m</sc>; <italic>lanes 5</italic> and <italic>10</italic> show RNAP plus CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> 20 mu<sc>m</sc>; <italic>lane 11</italic> shows Maxam and Gilbert G track. <italic>Lanes 1 - 5</italic> show reactions in the absence of cAMP; <italic>lanes 6 - 10</italic> show reactions in the presence of cAMP (2 m<sc>m</sc>). The location of the -10 element is indicated. <italic>B</italic>, DNase I footprint of P<italic>whiB1</italic> in the presence of an activating concentration of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> (2.5 mu<sc>m</sc>) and RNAP. <italic>Lanes 1</italic> and <italic>2</italic> show no protein; <italic>lanes 3</italic> and <italic>4</italic> show CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>; <italic>lanes 5</italic> and <italic>6</italic> show CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> plus RNAP; <italic>lane 7</italic> shows Maxam and Gilbert G track. The locations of the CRP1 (protected) and CRP2 (unprotected) sites are indicated by <italic>filled rectangles</italic>, as is the region of protection afforded by RNAP. The location of the -10 element is also marked. The hypersensitive site within CRP2 that appears in the presence of RNAP is indicated by the <italic>arrow</italic>. The footprints shown are typical of at least three experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0111006990005"/></fig><p>DNase I footprinting of the <italic>whiB1</italic> promoter in the presence of <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> RNAP and activating concentrations of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> (2.5 mu<sc>m</sc>) showed that RNAP could bind at the promoter when the CRP1 site was occupied and that this was accompanied by the appearance of an RNAP-dependent hypersensitive site at position -34, which is within the CRP2 site (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref><italic>B</italic>). The presence of the hypersensitive site is attributed to docking of the C-terminal domain of the RNAP alpha-subunit downstream of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> bound at CRP1.</p><p>To determine whether the effects of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> on <italic>whiB1</italic> transcription observed <italic>in vitro</italic> were also apparent <italic>in vivo</italic>, a promoter fusion containing DNA from -187 to 129 relative to the transcript start was fused upstream of a <italic>lac</italic> reporter gene, and transcription was estimated in <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> wild-type H37Rv and an isogenic <italic>Rv3676</italic> (<italic>crp</italic>) mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>). Under exponential growth conditions, expression of <italic>whiB1</italic> was decreased by ~3-fold in the CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> mutant (DeltaRv3676), consistent with CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>-dependent activation. An ~5-fold reduction in expression was observed when the CRP1 site was disabled, reflecting the absence of activation from CRP1 but retention of repression from CRP2. Accordingly, mutation of CRP2, without disrupting the -35 element (underlined) of the <italic>whiB1</italic> promoter (CGTAACACTA<underline>TTGACA</underline> to CcaAACACTA<underline>TTGACA</underline>), resulted in a small but reproducible increase in <italic>whiB1</italic> expression. Similarly, improvement of the CRP2 site (CGTAACACTATTGACA to CGTgACACTATTGACA) caused a reproducible decrease in <italic>whiB1</italic> expression. Disabling both CRP1 and CRP2 lowered beta-galactosidase activities by an amount similar to that observed using the unaltered promoter in the <italic>crp</italic> mutant. The <italic>in vivo</italic> data correlated well with the <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription data as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>, <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic>. Thus, when 2.5 mu<sc>m</sc> CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> was used in the <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription reactions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref><italic>D</italic>), the fold changes in transcription upon impairment of CRP-binding sites compared with the unaltered promoter were as follows: -3.5 to -2.4 when CRP1 was impaired; +1.2 to +1.6 when CRP2 was impaired; and -2.6 to -2.0 when both CRP1 and CRP2 were impaired. These values are similar to those obtained for transcription <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>) as follows: -4.6 when CRP1 was impaired; +1.2 when CRP2 was impaired; and -2.0 when CRP1 and CRP2 were impaired. Hence, the <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> experiments are consistent with a mechanism in which occupation of CRP1 enhances <italic>whiB1</italic> expression, whereas occupation of both CRP1 and CRP2 or of CRP2 alone represses <italic>whiB1</italic> expression in <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic>.</p><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>FIGURE 6.</label><caption><p><bold>Patterns of <italic>whiB1</italic> expression <italic>in vivo</italic> match those seen <italic>in vitro</italic>.</bold> beta-Galactosidase assays were performed on cell extracts from <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> H37Rv strains containing constructs with P<italic>whiB</italic>1 promoter linked to the <italic>lacZ</italic> reporter gene. These were as follows: the unaltered P<italic>whiB1</italic> (wild-type), P<italic>whiB1</italic> with the CRP1 site impaired (<italic>CRP1 impaired</italic>), P<italic>whiB1</italic> with the CRP2 site impaired (<italic>CRP2 impaired</italic>), and P<italic>whiB1</italic> with both the CRP1 and CRP2 sites impaired (<italic>CRP1 and 2 impaired</italic>). The effects of the mutations made in the CRP sites are shown as expression relative to that of the unaltered wild-type promoter to allow direct comparison with the <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription assays in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref><italic>D</italic>. Thus, the result for P<italic>whiB1</italic> with an impaired CRP1 site is shown as a <italic>gray bar</italic>; the result for P<italic>whiB1</italic> with an impaired CRP2 site is shown as a <italic>stippled bar</italic>, and the result for P<italic>whiB1</italic> with impaired CRP1 and CRP2 sites is shown as an <italic>open bar</italic>. In addition, on the <italic>right</italic> of the figure, the effect of improving the CRP2 site of P<italic>whiB1</italic> (CRP2 improved; <italic>diagonal stripes</italic>) as well as expression from unaltered P<italic>whiB1</italic> in H37Rv DeltaRv3676 (wild-type in <italic>crp</italic> mutant strain; <italic>horizontal stripes</italic>) is shown. The values shown are calculated from the mean beta-galactosidase activities from three bacterial cultures. All assays were done in triplicate and varied by &lt;15%. The expression relative to the unaltered <italic>whiB1</italic> promoter in <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> H37Rv was calculated by dividing the mean of the test condition by that obtained for the wild-type promoter and expressing this value as a fold change.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0111006990006"/></fig></sec></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The work described here shows that CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> is a homodimeric protein with one cAMP-binding site per protomer. This conclusion is substantiated by the crystal structure of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> bound to cAMP that was published during the review of this manuscript (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>). For <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> CRP, cAMP binding is cooperative; the first binding event is exothermic and the second is endothermic, and the sensory domain binding sites are saturated by micromolar concentrations of cAMP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>). This is not the case for CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> where the cAMP-binding sites are independent. The cAMP binding parameters for CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> are similar to those for cGMP binding to <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> CRP, except that the thermodynamic properties of these interactions are opposite; CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> cAMP binding has a positive enthalpy, whereas <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> CRP cGMP binding is exothermic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>). Recently, cAMP binding by <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> CRP has been shown to reorganize the major helices that form the dimer interface, thereby rotating the DNA binding domains so that they can interact with adjacent major grooves in target DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>). The differences in binding of cAMP by the <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> and <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> CRP proteins suggest that the signal transduction pathways that promote site-specific DNA binding might be different, and this might be reflected in the relatively small enhancement in DNA binding caused by addition of cAMP.</p><p>Comparison of the cAMP binding pockets of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>) and <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> CRP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>) reveals that most of the side chains that contact cAMP are either conserved or are conservatively substituted. The significant difference between the two proteins, in the context of the independent cAMP binding of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> compared with the cooperative cAMP binding of <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> CRP, is the substitution of Ser-128 in <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> CRP by Asn in CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>. Ser-128 makes a cross-subunit contact with cAMP in <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> CRP; <italic>i.e.</italic> Ser-128 of subunit B interacts with cAMP bound at subunit A (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref> shows that the N6 position of cAMP is able to donate two hydrogen bonds, which interact with the acceptor gamma oxygen atoms of Thr-127 of one subunit (subunit A) and of Ser-128 in the other subunit (subunit B) in <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> CRP. The latter two atoms are constrained to act as acceptors because they in turn donate hydrogen bonds to the main chain carbonyl acceptors of residues 123 in subunit A and 124 in subunit B, respectively. Residues 123 and 124 are located in the dimerization helices of the two <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> CRP subunits. The N6 of the adenosine moiety of cAMP therefore acts via Thr-127 of subunit A and Ser-128 of subunit B as a bridge between the main chains of the dimerization helices of the two subunits (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref><italic>A</italic>). A reciprocal interaction occurs when cAMP is bound in the other site of the CRP dimer, and hence the cAMP-binding sites of each protomer are connected. In CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>, the equivalent position to Ser-128 is occupied by Asn-135, and this does not significantly alter the position of cAMP. However, the Asn side chain makes two hydrogen bonds to cAMP; the ND2 of the Asn side chain can donate an H bond to the N7 of cAMP, and the OD1 atom can accept a hydrogen bond from one of the N6 donor hydrogen atoms (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref><italic>B</italic>). This pattern of interactions removes the possibility of the side chain of Asn-135 donating a hydrogen bond to the main chain carbonyl of residue 131 of subunit B. For this reason, replacement of the Ser by Asn at this position uncouples the cAMP-binding sites in CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>. Consistent with this interpretation, the substitution of Ser-128 by Ala in <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> CRP abolishes cooperative cAMP binding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>).</p><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>FIGURE 7.</label><caption><p><bold>Schematic diagram of hydrogen bonding contacts of the adenine groups of cAMP in the binding pockets of <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> and <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> CRP proteins.</bold> <italic>A</italic>, observed hydrogen bonds between cAMP and <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> CRP (Protein Data Bank code <ext-link ext-link-type="pdb" xlink:href="2cgp">2cgp</ext-link>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>). <italic>B</italic>, predicted hydrogen bonds between cAMP and CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> in which Ser-128 is replaced by Asn. Hydrogen bonds are shown as <italic>dotted arrows</italic> from donor to acceptor. Atoms referred to in the text are labeled.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0111006990007"/></fig><p>Although cAMP enhanced binding of recombinant CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> to target DNA, this enhancement was not comparable with that observed with <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> CRP, where DNA-binding affinity is enhanced by several orders of magnitude in the presence of 0.1 m<sc>m</sc> cAMP, allowing specific DNA binding at nanomolar concentrations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>). For CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>, a much less significant enhancement of DNA binding was observed, and higher concentrations of cAMP compared with <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> CRP were required. This may point to meaningful physiological changes in cAMP concentration in <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> occurring at higher levels than those in <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content>. Indeed, cAMP concentrations in mycobacteria have been reported to be rather high (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>), being ~100 - 200-fold greater than for <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content>. The high intracellular concentration of cAMP in <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> is consistent with the numerous adenylyl cyclases synthesizing cAMP. This and the reported increase in cAMP levels that occurs after infection of macrophages by pathogenic mycobacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6"> - </xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>) point to cAMP being an important signaling molecule in infection. The evidence presented here suggests that, perhaps as a consequence of the high intracellular concentrations of cAMP in <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic>, CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> has evolved a different mode of interaction with cAMP compared with the <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> paradigm, involving low affinity binding of cAMP to independent sites. Nevertheless, the response of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> to cAMP was very significant for expression of <italic>whiB1</italic>.</p><p>Several different classes of regulated bacterial promoters have been identified based on the locations of the binding sites for transcription activators. Promoters dependent on transcription factors bound at or close to -61 are known as class I promoters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>). At these promoters a specific region, known as activating region 1 (AR1), of the transcription factor interacts with the C-terminal domain of the alpha-subunit (alpha-CTD) of RNAP to activate transcription. A common alternative architecture is that of the class II promoters, in which the transcription factor binds to a site that overlaps the core -35 element of the promoter. At class II promoters multiple interactions between the transcription factor and RNAP are possible, including an AR1 interaction with alpha-CTD, an AR2 interaction with the RNAP alpha-subunit N-terminal domain, and interaction between AR3 and the sigma-subunit of RNAP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>). Class III promoters have transcription factors bound in tandem making both class I- and class II-type interactions with RNAP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>). The experiments described here and elsewhere show that expression of <italic>whiB1</italic> is dependent on CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> and that this requires a CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>-binding site centered 58.5 bp upstream of the transcript start, a class I location (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). However, it is now shown that there is a second, lower affinity, negatively acting CRP-binding site (CRP2 centered at -37.5) located immediately downstream of CRP1 that has significant implications for cAMP-CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>-mediated regulation of <italic>whiB1</italic> expression. The identification of a second class II CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>-binding site (CRP2) that is occupied when cAMP levels increase and inhibits <italic>whiB1</italic> activation by CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> bound at the class I site (CRP1) indicates that <italic>whiB1</italic> expression <italic>in vivo</italic> should be maximal at intermediate cAMP concentrations. Hence, the following model for cAMP-responsive <italic>whiB1</italic> expression provides the simplest explanation for the data described here. The locations of the two CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>-binding sites (-58.5 and -37.5) are such (centers of the sites are separated by 21 bp) that they are located on the same face of the DNA helix. At low concentrations of the CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>-cAMP complex, CRP1 is preferentially occupied (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref><italic>A</italic>); the alpha-CTD of RNAP docks downstream of CRP1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref><italic>B</italic>), and transcription of <italic>whiB1</italic> is activated via a class I mechanism (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>). Activation of class I promoters by <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> CRP occurs solely by recruiting RNAP to the promoter by increasing the binding constant for the formation of the RNAP-promoter closed complex (reviewed in Ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). However, the permanganate footprints suggest that low (nonrepressing; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref><italic>A</italic>) concentrations of CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> or CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>-cAMP do not significantly enhance open complex formation at the <italic>whiB1</italic> promoter compared with reactions lacking CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref><italic>A</italic>) indicating that a step after open complex formation is activated. Further experimental work will be needed to identify the mechanism by which this is achieved.</p><fig id="F8" position="float"><label>FIGURE 8.</label><caption><p><bold>Architecture of CRP-dependent promoters.</bold> The diagram shows the arrangement of nucleoprotein complexes formed at typical class I, class II, and class III CRP-dependent promoters. At class I promoters, the center of the CRP dimer (shown in ribbon form) is positioned at -61.5, -71.5, -81.5, or -91.5 upstream of the transcript start, placing it on the same face of the DNA helix (<italic>horizontal line</italic>) as RNAP (shown as <italic>unfilled ellipses</italic>). This arrangement allows the C-terminal domain of the RNAP alpha-subunit (alpha-CTD) to interact directly with activating region 1 (<italic>AR1</italic>) of the downstream subunit of the CRP dimer (&#x2666;). At class II promoters, the CRP dimer is centered at or close to -41.5 and is again on the same face of the DNA helix as RNAP. At these promoters multiple interactions between CRP and RNAP are possible, with contacts between AR1 of the upstream subunit of the CRP dimer and alpha-CTD, and between activating region 2 (AR2) of the downstream subunit of the CRP dimer and the N-terminal domain of the RNAP alpha-subunit (alpha-<italic>NTD</italic>; &#x25A0;), and activating region 3 (<italic>AR3</italic>) of the same CRP subunit and the RNAP sigma factor (&#x2605;). Class III promoters have tandem CRP sites in class I and class II locations allowing AR1, AR2, and AR3 contacts with RNAP. For <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> CRP, these protein-protein interactions recruit RNAP to CRP-dependent promoters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). For <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> P<italic>whiB1</italic> at low cAMP-CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> concentrations, CRP1 is occupied and expression is activated, not by RNAP recruitment but by enhancing a step after open complex formation, <italic>i.e.</italic> promoter clearance. At high cAMP-CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> concentrations, CRP1 and CRP2 are occupied. This arrangement has some similarities with the class III architecture, but because the CRP1 and CRP2 sites are immediately adjacent, there is insufficient space to accommodate the alpha-CTD between the tandem CRP dimers resulting in inhibition of transcription by preventing alpha-CTD from docking with DNA thereby inhibiting productive interaction of RNAP with P<italic>whiB1</italic> (indicated by the <italic>double-headed arrow</italic>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0111006990008"/></fig><p>At higher CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> or CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic>-cAMP concentrations, both CRP1 (class I position) and CRP2 (class II position) are occupied (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref><italic>A</italic>). Occupation of both CRP1 and CRP2 sites would leave little space between the two CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> dimers, preventing the formation of a typical class III nucleoprotein complex and thus the RNAP alpha-CTD is displaced, which is likely to result in either poor or unproductive binding of RNAP to the <italic>whiB1</italic> promoter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>). In this way, occupation of CRP2 by CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> antagonizes activation by CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic> bound at CRP1 resulting in inhibition of <italic>whiB1</italic> transcription. Because the concentration of cAMP in <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> increases during infection of macrophages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>), this suggests that <italic>whiB1</italic> might be expressed transiently during infection. Although the available microarray datasets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>) do not suggest that <italic>whiB1</italic> expression responds transiently at the time points sampled, this study indicates that the possibility that <italic>whiB1</italic> is transiently expressed during infection should be tested by obtaining high resolution long time course gene expression data to determine the significance of any such transient expression for <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> pathogenesis.</p></sec>
      <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
         <title>Supplementary Material</title>
         <supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
            <caption>
               <title>Supplemental Data</title>
            </caption>
            <media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_285_10_7016__index.html"/>
            <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword" xlink:href="supp_M109.047720_jbc.M109.047720-1.doc"/>
         </supplementary-material>
      </sec>
   </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="supported-by" id="FN1">
        <label>*</label>
        <p>This work was supported by The Wellcome Trust Grant 078731/Z/05/Z and the Medical Research Council.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="supplementary-material" id="FN2">
        <label>
          <inline-graphic xlink:href="sbox.jpg"/>
        </label>
        <p>The on-line version of this article (available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jbc.org">http://www.jbc.org</ext-link>) contains <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jbc.org/cgi/content/full/M109.047720/DC1">supplemental Figs. S1 - S3</ext-link>.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <fn-group content-type="abbreviations">
      <fn id="FN3">
        <label>2</label>
        <p>The abbreviations used are:
<def-list><def-item><term id="G1">CRP</term><def><p>cyclic AMP receptor protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G2">alpha-CTD</term><def><p>RNA polymerase alpha-subunit C-terminal domain</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G3">CRP<italic><sup>Mt</sup></italic></term><def><p><italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> CRP protein encoded by the gene <italic>Rv3676</italic></p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G4">RNAP</term><def><p>RNA polymerase.</p></def></def-item></def-list></p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>We thank Professor S. J. W. Busby (University of Birmingham) for the gift of the CCgalDelta4 plasmid and Luc Gaudreau and Jocelyn Beaucher (Universite de Sherbrooke, Canada) for advice on RNAP purification and for a control template for in vitro transcription assays.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dye</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheele</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pathania</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raviglione</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <source>J. Am. Med. Assoc.</source><volume>282</volume>, <fpage>677</fpage> - <lpage>686</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</source><volume>2</volume>, <fpage>569</fpage> - <lpage>577</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11483990</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>B. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</source><volume>1</volume>, <fpage>97</fpage> - <lpage>105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15035039</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>S. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brosch</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parkhill</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garnier</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Churcher</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>S. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eiglmeier</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gas</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name><name><surname>Tekaia</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Badcock</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Basham</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chillingworth</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Connor</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Devlin</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feltwell</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gentles</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamlin</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holroyd</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hornsby</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jagels</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krogh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>McLean</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moule</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Osborne</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajandream</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutter</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seeger</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Skelton</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Squares</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Squares</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sulston</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitehead</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrell</surname><given-names>B. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <source>Nature</source><volume>393</volume>, <fpage>537</fpage> - <lpage>544</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9634230</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamichhane</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nolan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishai</surname><given-names>W. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Nature</source><volume>460</volume>, <fpage>98</fpage> - <lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19516256</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lowrie</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackett</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ratcliffe</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1975</year>) <source>Nature</source><volume>254</volume>, <fpage>600</fpage> - <lpage>602</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">165421</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaak</surname><given-names>D. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonough</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>FEMS Immunol. Med. Microbiol.</source><volume>55</volume>, <fpage>68</fpage> - <lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19076221</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gazdik</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonough</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>J. Bacteriol.</source><volume>187</volume>, <fpage>2681</fpage> - <lpage>2692</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15805514</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Busby</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolb</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) in <source>Regulation of Gene Expression in Escherichia coli</source> (<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>E. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name></person-group> eds) pp. <fpage>255</fpage> - <lpage>279</lpage>, <publisher-name>R. G. Landes Co.</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Austin, TX</publisher-loc></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Busby</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebright</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><volume>293</volume>, <fpage>199</fpage> - <lpage>213</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10550204</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grainger</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurd</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holdstock</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Busby</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source><volume>102</volume>, <fpage>17693</fpage> - <lpage>17698</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16301522</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kirin</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sismeiro</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Danchin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertin</surname><given-names>P. N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>Microbiology</source><volume>148</volume>, <fpage>1553</fpage> - <lpage>1559</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11988530</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>O. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>von Hippel</surname><given-names>P. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><volume>200</volume>, <fpage>709</fpage> - <lpage>723</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3045325</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Browning</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Busby</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</source><volume>2</volume>, <fpage>57</fpage> - <lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15035009</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>McCue</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonough</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>J. Bacteriol.</source><volume>187</volume>, <fpage>7795</fpage> - <lpage>7804</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16267303</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rickman</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hutchinson</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Menendez</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Whalan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinds</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Colston</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buxton</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Mol. Microbiol.</source><volume>56</volume>, <fpage>1274</fpage> - <lpage>1286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15882420</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raghunand</surname><given-names>T. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishai</surname><given-names>W. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Microbiology</source><volume>152</volume>, <fpage>2749</fpage> - <lpage>2756</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16946269</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spreadbury</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pallen</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Overton</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Behr</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mostowy</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spiro</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Busby</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Microbiology</source><volume>151</volume>, <fpage>547</fpage> - <lpage>556</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15699203</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gazdik</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaak</surname><given-names>D. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonough</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Infect. Immun.</source><volume>75</volume>, <fpage>5509</fpage> - <lpage>5517</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17785469</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saldanha</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benjamin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strom</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spreadbury</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buxton</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>Infect. Immun.</source><volume>76</volume>, <fpage>2227</fpage> - <lpage>2234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18332206</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mukamolova</surname><given-names>G. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turapov</surname><given-names>O. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>D. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaprelyants</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kell</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>Mol. Microbiol.</source><volume>46</volume>, <fpage>623</fpage> - <lpage>635</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12410821</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>den Hengst</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buttner</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</source><volume>1780</volume>, <fpage>1201</fpage> - <lpage>1216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18252205</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jakimowicz</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheesman</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishai</surname><given-names>W. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chater</surname><given-names>K. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buttner</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><volume>280</volume>, <fpage>8309</fpage> - <lpage>8315</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15615709</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alam</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>FEBS J.</source><volume>276</volume>, <fpage>76</fpage> - <lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19016840</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crossman</surname><given-names>D. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mai</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guidry</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Voskuil</surname><given-names>M. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Renfrow</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steyn</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>PLoS Pathogens</source><volume>8</volume>, <fpage>e1000545</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19680450</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soliveri</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishai</surname><given-names>W. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chater</surname><given-names>K. F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <source>Microbiology</source><volume>146</volume>, <fpage>333</fpage> - <lpage>343</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10708372</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blazy</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baudras</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><volume>207</volume>, <fpage>783</fpage> - <lpage>796</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2547972</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Casadaban</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>S. N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>) <source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><volume>138</volume>, <fpage>179</fpage> - <lpage>207</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6997493</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Busby</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotlarz</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buc</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>) <source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><volume>167</volume>, <fpage>259</fpage> - <lpage>274</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6408264</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kubica</surname><given-names>G. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>T. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunbar</surname><given-names>F. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1972</year>) <source>Int. J. Syst. Bacteriol.</source><volume>22</volume>, <fpage>99</fpage> - <lpage>106</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snapper</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Melton</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mustafa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kieser</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>W. R.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <source>Mol. Microbiol.</source><volume>4</volume>, <fpage>1911</fpage> - <lpage>1919</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2082148</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lodge</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Busby</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <source>FEMS Microbiol. Lett.</source><volume>67</volume>, <fpage>221</fpage> - <lpage>225</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2109722</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>14</volume>, <fpage>3603</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3010244</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaston</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolb</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buc</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Minchin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Busby</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>18</volume>, <fpage>7243</fpage> - <lpage>7250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2259621</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B35">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Papavinasasundaram</surname><given-names>K. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>P. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Movahedzadeh</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenner</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Colston</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>E. O.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>Microbiology</source><volume>147</volume>, <fpage>3271</fpage> - <lpage>3279</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11739759</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B36">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sambrook</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>Molecular Cloning: A Laboratory Manual</source>, <edition>3rd Ed.</edition>, <publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Cold Spring Harbor, NY</publisher-loc></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B37">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wiseman</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williston</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandts</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>L. N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <source>Anal. Biochem.</source><volume>179</volume>, <fpage>131</fpage> - <lpage>137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2757186</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B38">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1972</year>) <source>Experiments in Molecular Genetics</source>, pp. <fpage>352</fpage> - <lpage>355</lpage>, <publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Cold Spring Harbor, NY</publisher-loc></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B39">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maxam</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>) <source>Methods Enzymol.</source><volume>65</volume>, <fpage>499</fpage> - <lpage>560</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6246368</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B40">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beaucher</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigue</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaques</surname><given-names>P. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brzezinski</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaudreau</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>Mol. Microbiol.</source><volume>45</volume>, <fpage>1527</fpage> - <lpage>1540</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12354223</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B41">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akter</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tundup</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasnain</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Int. J. Med. Microbiol.</source><volume>297</volume>, <fpage>451</fpage> - <lpage>457</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17702648</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B42">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Angulo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krakow</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><volume>262</volume>, <fpage>11315</fpage> - <lpage>11319</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3015965</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B43">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palaninathan</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruning</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thurman</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sacchettini</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><volume>284</volume>, <fpage>36581</fpage> - <lpage>36591</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19740754</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B44">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gorshkova</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>McKenney</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>F. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><volume>270</volume>, <fpage>21679</fpage> - <lpage>21683</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7665583</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B45">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Popovych</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tonelli</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebright</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalodimos</surname><given-names>C. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source><volume>106</volume>, <fpage>6927</fpage> - <lpage>6932</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19359484</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B46">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>I. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steitz</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><volume>198</volume>, <fpage>311</fpage> - <lpage>326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2828639</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B47">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Passner</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steitz</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source><volume>94</volume>, <fpage>2843</fpage> - <lpage>2847</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9096308</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B48">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorshkova</surname><given-names>I. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>McKenney</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>F. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><volume>271</volume>, <fpage>21273</fpage> - <lpage>21278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8702903</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B49">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Padh</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Venkitasubramanian</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1976</year>) <source>Microbios</source><volume>16</volume>, <fpage>183</fpage> - <lpage>189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">196160</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B50">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rohde</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abramovich</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Cell Host Microbe</source><volume>2</volume>, <fpage>352</fpage> - <lpage>364</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18005756</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B51">
        <label>51.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schnappinger</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrt</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Voskuil</surname><given-names>M. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mangan</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Monahan</surname><given-names>I. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolganov</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Efron</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Butcher</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nathan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoolnik</surname><given-names>G. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>J. Exp. Med.</source><volume>198</volume>, <fpage>693</fpage> - <lpage>704</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12953091</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>



